<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Nicholas Fox on Nicholas Fox</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Nicholas Fox on Nicholas Fox</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Nicholas Fox</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Selected Publications</title>
      <link>/publications_selected/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publications_selected/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Recent Publications</title>
      <link>/publications/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publications/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Maternal Immune Activation and Behavioral Outcomes in Adult Offspring</title>
      <link>/project/mia/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/mia/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This page will soon be updated with all of my Masters work - stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Measuring the Size of Hidden Populations</title>
      <link>/project/social-networks/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/social-networks/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Many people live with stigma, or some trait that devalues them in the view of others.  For some, this stigma can be concealed - sexual orientation or smoking can both be stigmatizing but can be kept secret from other people.  However, there are many times where it is important to know how many people identify with a particular stigma.  For example, drug users who use needles are at an increased risk for HIV and other bloodborne pathogens.  Sex workers are at an increased risk for HIV, sexually transmitted infection, and personal violence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When asked directly, individuals with concealable stigma have the option of either concealing their identity (denying their identity when asked) or reveal their identity.  This decision to conceal or reveal is a complex one that entails how likely it is they will be &amp;ldquo;outed&amp;rdquo; by their own behaviors or somebody else, the perceived repercussions of having their identity revealed, and the prospect of social support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way to try and count the number of people with concealable stigmas is to use social networks.  By tapping into the shared information that exists within social networks, researchers can glean the number of people have certain characteristcs by asking members of the general population.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am currently applying this methodology to academic social networks in an effort to measure the number of researchers who use questionable research practices (QRPs).  Use of these QRPs has led to an increase in the number of scientific findings that are not replicatable.  It is important to understand the number of researchers who engage in these questionable practices in order to construct meaningful interventions and to monitor the efficacy of these interventions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Immunology Has A Problem With Researcher Degrees of Freedom</title>
      <link>/post/immunology_degrees_of_freedom/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/immunology_degrees_of_freedom/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/findings.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;findings&#34; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Two scientists performing science. from the-scientist.com, July 2011&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just got back from the annual meeting of the Society for the Improvement of Psychological Science (SIPS) and had a great time talking to a number of psychologists looking to help promote open, reproducible science. It really got me thinking about all the different kinds of science I’ve been a part of in my undergraduate and graduate career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a very long time I was a cellular biologist. The most productive time of my tenure as a biologist was when I was studying Immunology. Immunology is the study of the immune system, which is a disparate organ system comprised of organs (spleen, thymus, lymph nodes) and white blood cells spread throughout the body. A big chunk of immunological research involves identifying different cell populations and how they react to different treatments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, do the CD8+ T cells (which are a type of white blood cell) of a Type I diabetic person activate more strongly than those from a non-diabetic? In this case, blood would be taken from Type I diabetic and non-diabetic participants, and the blood cells would be treated to an in vitro stimulation. Then, the cells would be observed for their activation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But how can one observe the activation of these cells? This is where a special type of measurement tool comes in: the flow cytometer. Flow cytometry is a process that allows a research to “scan” individual cells for surface receptors or proteins of interest. These can be used to identify specific cell populations. Cells that have a T Cell Receptor (TCR) and the CD3 surface protein are different than those that have a TCR, CD3, and the CD4 surface protein. By making scatter plots like the one below (where one axis is the CD3 protein and the other axis is the CD4 protein), researchers can identify cell populations of interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/flow_sample.png&#34; alt=&#34;flow_sample&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s say you are only interested in cells that are expressing CD3 but not expressing CD4. You may want to further explore the characteristics of this population (for example, maybe you want to see if they are more activated in Type 1 diabetics compared to non-diabetics). How do you select only this population? You could use some method of k-means clustering or k-nearest neighbors…or you could just draw a box around it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is what immunologists do. Sometimes it is an oval, or a static set of quadrants. The problem with this is the researcher’s degrees of freedom. When the researcher eyeballs what cells are the cells that will be chosen for analysis, that cannot be replicated by someone else. What are the odds two people will draw the exact same box given the exact same data when they’re using a manual selection tool?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is an example of when this can throw results into question:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/immunofigure_main.png&#34; alt=&#34;immunofigure_main&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On top are 3 sets of flow cytometry scatter plots, showing a comparison of the percent of cells that are CD25- (they don’t have that protein), Ly5.2+, CD4+, FoxP3+. This is a particular type of immune cell, and the point from this figure is that there are more of this cell type in the lamina propria (LP) and few in Peyer’s patches (PP) and the spleen (SP). The bottom shows the average percent for each of 6 mice per group (each point represents the percent of FoxP3+ cells per animal in the CD25-, Ly5.2+, CD4+ population(the boxed areas from the top)).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was curious if they were using the same boxes to inscribe these populations, so I stacked two of them on top of each other. Here is the result:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/immunofigure.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;immunofigure&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, this paper does not describe the decision making process in generating these selection boxes for these cell populations. They also did not indicate how many cells were collected from each animal, nor publish the scatter plots for the other 5 animals per each group. An obvious problem from this approach is selection bias. Researchers select the most obvious grouping of cells given the density plot. Whether or not this is the most correct approach is not accounted for, and many cells of interest may be lost because they did not fall perfectly with other cells.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is an additional issue with this type of data analysis. Each animal has a certain number of cells collected. This number is not reported and can vary by thousands of cells between animals. A percentage is calculated as “positive” for a certain phenotype (x% of cells are positive for this phenotype, and 1-x% of cells are negative). Depending on the phenotype, your population of interest may have already been subjected to several rounds of selection via hand-drawn selection boxes. In the end, there are only two possible states for a cell: either positive or negative - this is a binary outcome. A percentage of positive cells is calculated, and those percentages are averaged across animals by condition (see the bottom panel of the figure above). Those conditions are then compared via t test (as reported in the methods section).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is an problem with nesting here - the cells being collected and measured are nested within animal. For animals who have fewer cells collected, each individual cell will carry more weight when falling as either phenotype positive or phenotype negative. In other words, in an animal with 5,000 cells collected, each cell that is positive will increase the animal’s percent positive to a higher magnitude than an animal with 10,000 cells collected. This problem is compounded the further down into hand-drawn population selections you get: at each step, cell population differences between animals may increase or decrease depending on how those selection boxes are drawn by the researcher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One solution would be to control for this variation using multi-level or hierarchal linear models. This would help account for the differences in cell counts between animals. Some animals may have fewer cells collected for a variety of reasons, though that should not afford their phenotypes increased weight in the final analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another solution is to use clustering analysis to identify cell populations. Doing this removes a degree of freedom from the researcher, which is especially important when cell populations may be relatively close together on a given axis. This also gives more power to others looking to replicate findings: On a different machine with a different technician, populations may look different, and having an analytic approach that is robust to variation across observer is important for reproducibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, it is important to note that this approach to data collection is extremely common and widespread. I did a quick search of “FoxP3” on google scholar and many papers had published flow cytometry with questionable approaches to population selection and mean group comparisons. For immunology to progress in this time of increased scrutiny of data prep, analysis, and reproduction, the field will need to reexamine its relationship with flow cytometry and generate new, robust protocols.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(black and white figure from:
Small intestine lamina propria dendritic cells promote de novo generation of Foxp3 T reg cells via retinoic acid. Cheng-Ming Sun, Jason A. Hall, Rebecca B. Blank, Nicolas Bouladoux, Mohamed Oukka, J. Rodrigo Mora, Yasmine Belkaid. Journal of Experimental Medicine Aug 2007, 204 (8) 1775–1785; DOI: 10.1084/jem.20070602)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cash Rules Everything Around Me: R01 Funding &amp; the Diversity of Ideas</title>
      <link>/talk/sips2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/sips2017/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this talk, I cover some of the trends in R01 funding from 2000 to 2014.  Of interest is the effect of the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act (ARRA), also known as The 2009 Stimulus.  As an effort to reduce the negative economic impact of the 2008 Recession, the federal government increased the budgets of many public institutions, including the National Institutes of Health (NIH).  In this talk, I present how ARRA dollars changed the distribution of R01 funds to downstream scientists. I conclude with recommendations for diversifying R01 funding to more scientists, spreading the money across more labs to decrease waste spending and increase diversity of ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This work is in preperation for an upcoming publication.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The hypocritical silence of “free speech” academics on net neutrality</title>
      <link>/post/free_speech_net_neutrality/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/free_speech_net_neutrality/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/marketplace_ideas_comic.png&#34; alt=&#34;marketplace_of_ideas&#34; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Image from Cagle.com - Kevin Siers, Charlotte Observer 2015&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently there have been several highly publicized protests of speakers on college campuses. Most, but not all, of these speakers have been associated with conservative politics or viewpoints that challenge current ideas on social justice (Ann Coulter, Milo Yiannopoulos, Charles Murray, etc). At Heterodox Academy and across most mainstream news outlets, academics and college administrators have spoken up about the possible threats to free speech on campus posed by student groups protesting to silence these speakers. They argue that the best way to combat speech you do not agree with is more speech, and that when those speakers are silenced, their ideas are never openly challenged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While many free speech-defending academics uphold the university as a “marketplace of ideas” (John Stewart Mill), this is a tired notion that is no longer true. &lt;strong&gt;There is a new marketplace of ideas, and it is the Internet.&lt;/strong&gt; On the Internet, controversial speakers on both the Left and the Right have a free platform to generate and promote their ideas to the public. The internet is widely available for consumption, at home or on the go - much more widely available than a lecture hall on some college campus. A university talk is no longer the place where ideas are batted around in search of the truth - it is now where books and podcasts are hyped to increase sales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How could students protest a speaker if they did not already know their platform? It is easy to research Milo, or Ann Coulter on the Internet today and know their viewpoint in five minutes. Campus talks are no longer required to gain insight into opinions you may not agree with - most of us carry the tools we need for that in our pocket or backpack. &lt;strong&gt;We are now living in a world where opposing opinions are easier to come across and argue against than ever before&lt;/strong&gt;, just scroll through the comments section of any news article to see for yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This ability for individuals across the political spectrum to voice their opinions on the Internet unfettered has recently come under attack. Back in 2015, the FCC adopted rules to protect net neutrality, meaning Internet service providers (ISPs) could not interfere with the generation or access of information on the web. At the time, this was seen as a victory in protecting free speech across the Internet. However, in May 2017, the new FCC chairperson appointed under President Trump, Ajit Pai, has spearheaded actions to roll back these FCC rules protecting equal access to material on the Internet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this is what is so baffling about the deafening silence from academics when it comes to net neutrality. On the one hand, student protests on campus are seen as a real threat to the rich variety of thought at our universities. On the other hand, when the largest democratic arena of free thought has its freedom threatened by large Internet service providers…there is hardly an objection. Where is the academic concern over ISPs gating the kinds of information you can find on the Internet?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an issue far more dangerous to free speech than a conservative podcaster having their invited talk on campus canceled. The number of total students across all universities (20.5 million in the U.S) is dwarfed by the number of people using the Internet (240.7 million in the U.S) to inform their opinions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The real outrage on campus should be focused on these academics who have yet to respond to the largest threat to free speech yet.&lt;/strong&gt; I call on my fellow academics (students, faculty, and the professorship) to redirect some of the energy being spent on campus climate towards the greater threat of a less accessible Internet.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Person Re-Identification System For Mobile Devices</title>
      <link>/publication/person-re-identification/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/person-re-identification/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;More detail can easily be written here using &lt;em&gt;Markdown&lt;/em&gt; and $\rm \LaTeX$ math code.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mobile visual clothing search</title>
      <link>/publication/clothing-search/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/clothing-search/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;More detail can easily be written here using &lt;em&gt;Markdown&lt;/em&gt; and $\rm \LaTeX$ math code.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
